Derek Wilson

Nationality British Citizen, New Zealand Resident email mail@derekwilson.net

Synopsis

Derek is an excellent software developer with strong programming and design skills. He has a wealth of experience in building successful software products. He has demonstrated his ability to complete complex tasks and has also needed to adapt and extend his knowledge base in an ever changing technology environment.

He works well in multi-disciplinary teams covering the complete cycle from design to implementation. He is passionate about creating beautiful and useful software products using a wide spectrum of tools and techniques.

Skills

Programming Technologies

Android Studio, Java, Junit, Mockito, Android OS v2 to 7 – 3 years

Microsoft .NET Framework (v1 to v4), C# and VB.NET - $\,10+$ years

Microsoft Visual C++ (Version 1.0 to 6.0 & MFC Version 2.0 to 6.0) – 10+ years

NUnit, xUnit, NCover, PartCover, Rhino Mocks and Moq - 5 years

HTML/JavaScript for -10+ years

Microsoft IIS – 10+ years

Microsoft SQL Server (2000 to 2012) - 7 years

Oracle (8i, 9i and 10i) – 5 years

Microsoft Enterprise Library – 5 years

Microsoft .NET Compact Framework (v1.0 and v2.0) – 2 years

Microsoft Embedded Visual C++ (Version 3.0 and Version 4.0) – 2 years

Other Programming Technologies

Microsoft Visual Basic (Version 5 and 6)

Microsoft Win32 SDK for Windows Desktop and Mobile Platforms

Codesmith, .NetTiers, LLBLGen, NHibernate

SQLite v3, SQLServer CE 3 and 4

Employment Experience

Apr 2014 – Current, Xero

3 Market Lane, Wellington 6142, New Zealand

At Xero we are building beautiful on-line accounting software for small businesses. Xero is an online software as a service product. We are a young company strongly growing towards one million customers.

Key technologies: Android Studio, Java, Dagger2, Junit, Mockito, GIT, Jenkins, Jira

I am a **senior android developer** on the Xero core mobile team. Xero has over 100,000 downloads and is a key component in the core platform. I work in a medium sized development team taking responsibility for improving the software architecture by promoting the use of **IoC**, as well as **MVP** and repository patterns to promote code isolation and the use of **automated unit tests** using Junit and Mockito.

Feb 2012 – Mar 2014, Xero

3 Market Lane, Wellington 6142, New Zealand

Key technologies: C#, MVC, Ext JS, LLBLGen, xUnit, SQL Server, GIT, Team City, Jira

I was a **lead developer** on the SubXero team. SubXero is a large enterprise level subscription billing system that is used to invoice all Xero's customers and to process their payments. The UI controls the billing process, administers discounts, enables customers to administer their payments and provides support to customer care. The core billing system raises and processes payments for approaching 100,000 invoices a month.

My role covered leading a small team of developers, **designing and building** enhancements to the software, acting as the **primary technical contact** for the financial management team. The team used **agile techniques** including stand-ups and TDD.

I won the Xero Speed Demon award for best optimisation as part of my work in scaling out the billing system. In 2013 I earned a "shout out" award of appreciation from the CEO at the annual end of year event.

Jan 2009 – Jan 2012, Swinton Insurance, Web Team

6 Great Marlborough Street, Manchester M1 5SW, UK

Swinton Insurance are the leading high street insurance broker in the UK. I worked for the web team which is responsible for the internet quote and buy system used by the public, internal sales staff and also aggregator sites

such as comparethemarket.com. The quote and buy system is a high volume mission critical system accounting for a significant proportion of the company revenue stream - it can deliver up to 500,000 quotes a day.

Key technologies: C#, ASP.NET, MVC, SQLServer, NUnit, JavaScript, jQuery, NHibernate, TFS

My role was as a **lead developer**. I was responsible for designing technical solutions to satisfy business and compliance needs, with larger pieces of work I produced a design to guide other developer's work. I also attended code reviews for other teams within the group. The development used **agile practices**, with stand-ups, TDD/BDD development and continuous integration using **CruiseControl**. I was part of the team that ported the main web site from **ASP.NET** to **MVC** utilising **IoC** and extended the tests to include the **JavaScript** using **Jasmine**.

I also led the development of a multimillion pound system to handle renewal pricing. Implementing a complex pricing model the system utilised **SQL Server**, **NHibernate**, **IoC** using **Castle Windsor**, and **MVC**.

Jan 2007 – Dec 2008, PricewaterhouseCoopers UK Indirect Tax Practice,

PricewaterhouseCoopers are the largest professional services company in the world. I worked for a group which provides professional quality products for the tax practice and for external customers. I worked with a small team within the Tax Practice based in Manchester who provide services and technology solutions to large clients to optimise their indirect tax liability.

Key technologies: C#, ASP.NET, SQL Server, VB.NET, HTML, NUnit

My role was as a **lead developer**, it was my responsibility to **design technology architectures** that will satisfy the business requirements and fit in with the centrally planned architecture provided by PricewaterhouseCoopers' internal IT organisation and their outsourcing partners for server hosting and other services.

In addition to this I led a team to develop and deploy a web solution, using ASP.NET, Enterprise Library, and SQL Server, for use by external clients to enable them to prepare and electronically file VAT100 tax returns with HMRC, Reveal. I instigated the use of code generation and OR mapping using Codesmith and .NetTiers.

I was part of an international team that spent some time each year constructing, documenting and deploying a software development framework to provide developers with a starting point for developing **ASP.NET v2** web sites that are to be hosted by PwC. The framework acts as a bridge between standard technologies such as **ASP.NET, Enterprise Library, XML, XSLT** and cryptography and shows how these technologies can be used within the PwC environment. The framework is used extensively by the vast majority of .NET projects in the UK and the US.

Jan 2001 – Dec 2006, PricewaterhouseCoopers US IAS Tax Technology Practice,

Based in Manchester and San Jose I worked for the International Assignment Services (IAS) Practice in San Jose California. We were a small team dedicated to providing services for large multinational clients to facilitate providing a range of financial service where the user base is working on international assignments.

Primary technologies: C#, ASP.NET, ASP, SQL Server, Oracle, VB6, HTML

I was **lead developer**, my role included specifying, designing, constructing, documenting and deploying an **IIS**. **NET** based web site construction framework that has been used by developers in the US, Europe and India to produce web sites for the IAS practice. The framework provides security services, page layout tools, **Oracle**, **SQL Server** and **XML** data access layers as well as **XSLT** cross browser **HTML/client script** rendering. This framework was first implemented using **IIS/ASP/VB** and then using **Microsoft .NET**.

I also designed and implemented a number of complete web sites where I took responsibility to deliver a complete end-to-end solution, for example GlobalSTAR and Assignee.com. These public sites cater for IAS practice clients, in excess of 150,000 users, and handles 60,000 tax return submissions per year.

Mar 98 – Dec 2000, PricewaterhouseCoopers UK Corporate Tax Practice,

The Corporate Tax Practice is responsible for completing tax returns for large external clients.

Key technologies: Visual C++, MFC, Win32

My role was as **project manager** and developer for Arena, a spreadsheet based development framework. The product was a large-scale project using **Microsoft Visual C++** and **Visual Basic** as well as third party class libraries. Arena was used to create PowerTax, which is used by the UK Tax practice to process over 90% of UK corporate compliance computations.

Mar 95 – Feb 98, Andrew Network Products,

Andrew Network Products (now NLynx Systems) is a significant supplier of AS/400 connectivity products. They have an extensive catalogue from emulation software to cabling for both IBM PC and Apple Mac markets.

Key technologies: Visual C++, MFC, Win32, AS/400

In 1995 Andrew NP were faced with declining sales of their Windows 3.x products. I was employed to **design** and **oversee development** of a **32 bit** product in **Visual C++**, for both **Windows 95 and Windows NT** to enable Andrew NP to recapture market share. Within 12 months we had produced ES/95, a product that supplied terminal and printer emulation for IBM AS/400 systems over a variety of connection methods, Twinax, TCP/IP and SNA Server. In a comparatively small market ES/95 showed strong sales turning over \$2 million a year.

My role within the team was to focus the design to ensure a coherent and consistent product and to implement the more complex components. I was also responsible for all engineering production including foreign language and OEM versions. I monitored and assisted other members of the team, **reported progress** and **identified potential problems and opportunities** to my manager. The development team were responsible for everything from the original concept all the way through to producing the master CD for duplication.

Sep 89 - Feb 95, The National Computing Centre Limited,

The NCC is the leading membership organisation in information technology in the UK. The key activities for the company are IT consultancy and development of software products. I was part of the software development team in the Systems Engineering Division.

Between June '93 and Feb '95 I was development team leader for CentreLink for Windows, a client/server data retrieval tool. This product enables client PC's running **Windows** to access data on mainframe and UNIX hosts via a variety of communication protocols from TCP/IP and IPX ODI to VT100. Prior to this I was development team leader for ASSET, a multi-user CASE (SSADM) support tool.

Jan 87 - Aug 89, The Rigby Group PLC,

Initially I was employed to develop and refine a **GUI multimedia** Computer Based Training Authoring Tool for IBM PC computers under GEM/MSDOS. As the project matured I was responsible for **supervising contractors** and being team leader to a small development team.

Other Experience

Jan 2016 – current, wrist-spin

wrist-spin is a live cricket score display for Pebble watches. Its designed to keep you up to date with your favourite team without having to get your phone out all the time.

Key technologies: C, Javascript, Pebble SDK, Atom, Visual Studio Code, Ubuntu, GIT

The app is available from the Pebble store, with over 250 active users it is the second most popular cricket app. It is an example of C SDK development in a wearable environment.

Jul 2015 – current, Recommender

Recommender is an Android application to store, organize and share personal recommendations. Its designed to be used in person where you want to pass on a recommendation to a friend.

Key technologies: Java, Android Studio, Dagger2, RxAndroid, Retrofit, SqlBrite, Roboelectric, JUnit

This android application is available in the Google Play Store. The code in an example of isolating UI, business logic and data access using MVP and IoC.

Jan 2010 – current, PodcastUtilities

PodcastUtilities is an open source podcast downloader and synchroniser. I work on the project with a colleague in my spare time.

Key technologies: C#, Mercurial, NUnit, Rhino Mocks, PartCover, MTP

This project is not intended to be a serious competitor to iTunes however it may be useful to a niche market. It is intended as a learning exercise to get familiar with using **Mercurial** and **distributed software development**. An open source project of this nature is an excellent opportunity to **collaborate** and **review** each others code as well as giving any prospective employer an opportunity to see the quality of the code I can produce.

Jan 2003 – Dec 2007, Worldolio,

Worldolio is a world clock style application for the Windows Mobile platform.

Key technologies: C#, .NET Compact Framework, ASP.NET, WebServices, Embedded C++

What began as an evenings and weekend project grew until we **launched a commercial (shareware) product,** Worldolio. This world clock style application made use of **native C++ Win32** code for a responsive user interface and a **.NET Compact Framework** client to download weather forecast data from a custom ASP.NET web service using a partially connected model.

Worldolio has been downloaded over 1,000 times. It is a strong indication of the quality of the software that is has a sales conversion rate of approaching 10%, well above the average for shareware and has had less than 10 support emails over the entire lifetime of the product.

Training and Development

ICAgile Certified Professional
WDCNZ 20012, 2013, 2015
ASP.NET Connections, 2008
Mix, 2007
.NET Master Class, Juval Lowy, iDesign, 2006
European Software Conference for the Independent Developer, 2006
TechEd, 2004 and 2005
Enterprise Microsoft.NET Development, Learning Tree, 2002
ASP.NET Connections, 2001
Essential ATL, DevelopMentor, 2000
Introduction to Corporate Tax, PwC 1999
Visual C++ Developer's Conference, 1998

Education/Qualifications

Oct 81 - May 85, Manchester Polytechnic, Oxford Road, Manchester, M1 5GD.

BSc (Hons) Combined Studies (2nd Class 1st Division) Computer Science/Chemistry

Interests

Bridge, Badminton, Cricket, Cycling, Reading and playing with my MediaCenter